<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id/>
      <journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
      <issn/>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name/>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Digital Succession Identifiers</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">0000-0002-5014-4809</contrib-id>
          <name>
            <surname>Ellerman</surname>
            <given-names>E. Castedo</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>castedo@castedo.com</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date date-type="eprint" publication-format="electronic" iso-8601-date="2022-08-09">
        <day>9</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2022</year>
      </pub-date>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2022, Ellerman et al</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2022</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Ellerman et al</copyright-holder>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
          <license-p>This document is distributed under a Creative Commons
Attribution 4.0 International license.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p><bold>STAGE</bold>: Early draft</p>
        <p><bold>DOCUMENT TYPE</bold>: Technical Specification</p>
        <p>This is a specification of Digital Succession Identifiers implemented
over git.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>This is a technical specification of <italic>Digital Succession
  Identifiers</italic>. A non-technical background and motivation for
  this new technology can be found in the
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://perm.pub/czdv8PyJKF7LneTnaVT6pgAKyh8/0.1">description
  of the perm.pub pilot project</ext-link>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="digital-successions">
      <title>Digital successions</title>
      <p>A digital succession contains digital objects. A digital object in
  this context is a fixed finite collection of bits. A computer file is
  an example of a digital object. A file system directory (folder) can
  also be represented as a digital object by both
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Git">git</ext-link><xref alt="1" rid="ref-enwikiU003A1109231861" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>
  and
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://softwareheritage.org">Software
  Heritage</ext-link>
  <xref alt="2" rid="ref-cosmo_referencing_2020" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>.
  Conceptually, each digital object in a digital succession is a new
  edition of a previous digital object. Each edition is assigned a
  number which determines its order. Although a digital succession
  expands, each digital object within the succession does not
  change.</p>
      <p>A digital succession is also digitally signed. In the simplest
  case, a single user signs using a digital key that is verified to be
  for that user. In this specification, the digital signature is made
  using a
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pretty_Good_Privacy">PGP
  key</ext-link>
  <xref alt="3" rid="ref-enwikiU003A1108847090" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>.</p>
      <p>When a digital succession is created, it consists of only a
  digitally signed genesis record and no digital object editions. The
  <italic>Digital Succession Identifier</italic> is an intrinsic
  identifier
  <xref alt="4" rid="ref-di_cosmo_2044_2022" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> of
  the genesis record.</p>
      <sec id="digital-successions-implemented-via-git">
        <title>Digital successions implemented via git</title>
        <p>In the git implementation, the genesis record is a signed initial
    git commit with an empty tree (and no parent).</p>
        <p>To expand the digital succession, additional commits are made
    using the same signing key. The git tree associated with each
    additional commit is not a new edition of the digital object. The
    git tree of a commit is a full succession record. The full
    succession record is a directory of all editions to date. The top
    level directory consists of only subdirectories named as
    non-negative numbers. Within each number named subdirectory is an
    entry named <monospace>object</monospace>. This entry is a digital
    object edition in the digital succession. This digital object can be
    a file (git blob) or a directory (git tree).</p>
        <p>For example, when a single file is added as edition 1, the full
    succession record is a directory with one path of
    <monospace>1/object</monospace> to a git blob which is edition
    1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="textual-representation-of-a-digital-succession-identifier">
        <title>Textual representation of a Digital Succession
    Identifier</title>
        <p>Given a digital succession genesis record, git and open-source
    software that emulate git, can calculate a 20 byte binary hash which
    identifies that digital succession. In most uses of git, this 20
    byte binary hash is represented textually as a 40 digit hexadecimal
    number. In this specification, the textual identifier of the 20 byte
    binary hash is a 27 character representation in standard base64url
    format (RFC
    4648)<xref alt="5" rid="ref-rfc4648" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>.</p>
        <p>It is worth noting, that when a new digital succession (git
    initial commit) is created, a user can choose not to use it and
    instead immediately create a new one with a different base64url text
    representation. There is little cost in not using empty digital
    successions and recreating new genesis records (git initial commits)
    until an acceptable base64url identifier is found.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="design-choice-rationales">
      <title>Design Choice Rationales</title>
      <sec id="use-of-the-term-edition">
        <title>Use of the term edition</title>
        <p>The term edition is used to refer to a digital object in the
    digital succession. Part of the motivation is to avoid confusion
    with the many uses of the term version. For instance, version can be
    used to refer to versions of a digital object that are not added as
    editions. One can also talk about versions of the entire succession
    record.</p>
        <p>This language is partly due to the initial application of digital
    successions for scientific articles. Although there are rarely new
    versions of scientific articles after they are published, it is well
    established that scientific textbooks are published in multiple
    <italic>editions</italic>.</p>
        <p>In the initial application of digital successions, documents are
    the digital object. A single edition of a document might be
    presented in different HTML and PDF <italic>versions</italic>, even
    though they are the same <italic>edition</italic> of a document.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="separation-of-git-history-from-edition-history">
        <title>Separation of git history from edition history</title>
        <p>A significant design choice is to not directly rely on git commit
    history to determine the succession of editions. Git commit history
    is conducive to accurately and faithfully recording the actions
    performed with git. However this often can be inflexible and
    confusing for establishing a clean linear history. That Software
    Heritage automatically preserves git commits compounds the risk that
    git commits do not correspond well, or perhaps even prevent, an
    intended clean linear history. It seems likely that there will be
    situations where having merge commits and non-linear git commit
    history will be convenient.</p>
        <p>Having edition history separate from git history also provides a
    potential path for an enhancement akin to retractions of specific
    editions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="use-of-base64url-rather-than-hexadecimal">
        <title>Use of base64url rather than hexadecimal</title>
        <p>The textual identifier is in base64url (Base64 with URL and
    filename safe alphabet) as specified in RFC 4648
    <xref alt="5" rid="ref-rfc4648" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>. Both this
    format and hexadecimal have pros and cons.</p>
        <p>As mentioned in the introduction to the textual representation,
    there is no obligation to use the Digital Succession Identifier
    (DSI) generated by a brand new digital succession. If a DSI is
    unacceptable to the creator of a new digital succession, a new DSI
    can be easily generated. Helper tools could perform this function
    for users by default.</p>
        <p>The main con to base64url is that it can contain characters which
    are more prone to copy errors when transmitted through human sight.
    Certain fonts and handwriting can make poor or no distinction
    between certain character pairs. For example, some popular sans
    serif fonts make no visual distinction between capital I and
    lowercase l.</p>
        <p>The main pro to base64url is that it is 27 characters rather than
    40. Future upgrades to DSI will likely make those lengths even
    larger, and the difference greater. Given that DSIs are used in
    contexts similar to DOIs, it is likely more acceptable to adopters
    to use 27 characters which is very typical for a long DOI, rather
    than 40 characters. Displaying an ID of 27 characters rather than 40
    characters also fits better on web pages rendered on mobile devices.
    27 characters are less like to be hidden by showing ellipsis,
    horizontal scroll regions or shrunk into extremely small fonts.</p>
        <p>This design decision is partly made on the belief that the
    copy-via-human-sight issue is increasingly mitigated by a few
    technology trends:</p>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <label>1)</label>
            <p>computer system are relied upon more and more via more
        reliable copying mechanisms such as clicking on hyperlinks,
        copy-and-paste, and QR codes instead of visual copying and
        handwriting.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <label>2)</label>
            <p>Websites tend to switch to using appropriate fonts for code
        like base64url IDs, when output into HTML. The same applies for
        tools that automatically produce PDFs from computer data.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <label>3)</label>
            <p>human-to-computer interfaces, such as input fields of
        Internet connected software, tend to add features like
        autocomplete and search disambiguation for typos, when
        sufficient need arises for such a feature.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="minutiae">
      <title>Minutiae</title>
      <list list-type="bullet">
        <list-item>
          <p>An edition number must be a positive integer strictly less than
      65,536 (2 to the 16th power). Edition number zero is reserved for
      special future use.</p>
        </list-item>
      </list>
    </sec>
    <sec id="references">
      <title>References</title>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref-cosmo_referencing_2020">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cosmo</surname>
              <given-names>Roberto Di</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruenpeter</surname>
              <given-names>Morane</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zacchiroli</surname>
              <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Referencing Source Code Artifacts: A Separate Concern in Software Citation</article-title>
          <source>Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</source>
          <year iso-8601-date="2020-03">2020</year>
          <month>03</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2022-09-05">2022</year>
            <month>09</month>
            <day>05</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <issn>1521-9615, 1558-366X</issn>
          <uri>https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8946737/</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/MCSE.2019.2963148</pub-id>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-di_cosmo_2044_2022">
        <element-citation publication-type="article-journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Di Cosmo</surname>
              <given-names>Roberto</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruenpeter</surname>
              <given-names>Morane</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zacchiroli</surname>
              <given-names>Stefano</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>204.4 Identifiers for Digital Objects: The case of software source code preservation.</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022-08">2022</year>
          <month>08</month>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">
            <year iso-8601-date="2022-09-05">2022</year>
            <month>09</month>
            <day>05</day>
          </date-in-citation>
          <uri>https://osf.io/kde56/</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17605/OSF.IO/KDE56</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-enwikiU003A1109231861">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <string-name>Wikipedia contributors</string-name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Git — Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <uri>https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Git&amp;oldid=1109231861</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-enwikiU003A1108847090">
        <element-citation>
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <string-name>Wikipedia contributors</string-name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pretty good privacy — Wikipedia, the free encyclopedia</article-title>
          <year iso-8601-date="2022">2022</year>
          <uri>https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Pretty_Good_Privacy&amp;oldid=1108847090</uri>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref-rfc4648">
        <element-citation publication-type="report">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Josefsson</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Base16, Base32, and Base64 data encodings</article-title>
          <publisher-name>RFC Editor; Internet Requests for Comments; RFC Editor</publisher-name>
          <year iso-8601-date="2006-10">2006</year>
          <month>10</month>
          <issn>2070-1721</issn>
          <uri>https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc4648.txt</uri>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17487/RFC4648</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
